(
"ai_sub_version": "2.9.1",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 7,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 15,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.1-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true
),
"gemini_cli": (
"timeout": 600,
"overwrite_system_prompt": false
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch"
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"run": 5,
"max": 5,
"delay": 30
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false
)
ヨォー
Yooooh!
レーザービーム
Laser Beam
ストレイト
Straight...
ドキドキする
My heart is pounding
視線はまるでレーザービーム
My gaze is like a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing through my heart with a fizz
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
実る果実が
Ripe fruit...
水を弾いて
...repelling water
キラキラしてる
Resembles the...
光に似てる
...sparkling light
グラウンドに立つ
Your figure standing...
キミの姿が
...on the playground
まぶしくて 少し
Is dazzling, and...
照れちゃうけど
...I get a little shy
ストレイト
Straight...
まっすぐだね保存
...you're so straightforward, aren't you?
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム保存
Love is surely a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの保存
Piercing through my heart with a fizz
虹色のラブビーム保存
A rainbow-colored love beam
ふたりを繋ぐ保存
The secret light...保存
秘密の光
...that connects the two of us
あの日見つけた
The secret light...
秘密の光
...I found that day
恋の瞬間
The moment of love...
音は止まって
...sound stops
時間はスローリーに
Time moves slowly...
恋の光線
...a beam of love
ストレイト
Straight...
ドキドキする
My heart is pounding
視線はまるでレーザービーム
My gaze is like a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing through my heart with a fizz
虹色のラブビーム保存
A rainbow-colored love beam
ストレイト
Straight...
まっすぐだね保存
...you're so straightforward, aren't you?保存
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム保存保存保存
Love is surely a laser beam保存保存
心をシュワりと突き刺すの保存保存保存
Piercing through my heart with a fizz保存保存
虹色のラブビーム保存保存保存保存
A rainbow-colored love beam保存保存
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
Come one, come all, take a look!
始まりました！らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ！
It has begun! Raden's new outfit reveal 3D live!
今宵はまだまだこれから！皆さん、一緒に盛り上がっていきましょう！
Tonight is just getting started! Everyone, let's fire things up together!
尽きない好奇心 素晴らしいジャポニズムに触れて
An endless curiosity, touching upon wonderful Japonism...
令和の風雲児 皆々にお届けいたしましょう
The child of the winds and clouds of Reiwa, let's deliver it to everyone!
饒舌に情熱 伝えたい愛に溢れている
A passionate eloquence, overflowing with the love I want to convey...
無知の知がきっと 素敵な始まりになるんだよ
The awareness of my ignorance will surely be a wonderful beginning!
知って欲しい たらふく味わって
I want you to know, to savor it to the fullest...
尊い 人生
...this precious life.
紐解いた歴史に 心惹かれていく
My heart is drawn to the history we've unraveled.
遥か遠く 電波に乗って あなたまで
Riding the airwaves from far away to reach you...
この想い 純粋に伝えたい 新しい世界 見せてあげる
I want to purely convey these feelings. New world... I'll show you!
開口一番やっちゃって
Right off the bat, let's do it!
破天荒に型破って
Unprecedented, breaking the mold!
金字塔パンチライン 時を超え
A monumental punchline, transcending time!
出囃子に乗せて
Set it to our theme music!
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
Come one, come all, take a look!
はい、はい！
Yeah, yeah!
はい！
Yeah!
はい、はい！
Yeah, yeah!
はい！
Yeah!
浪漫を抱いた人生を
A life filled with romance...
丸ごと賭けて傾きましょ
...let's risk it all and live wildly!
刹那に生きた足跡を
The footprints left by living in the moment,
偉大な先人と共に
together with the great pioneers.
洒落た口火切って手招く
Light a stylish fuse, beckon...
芸事の深淵
...into the abyss of the performing arts.
相反する感情 愛憎
Conflicting emotions of love and hate,
超えていく感動
surpassed by the moving inspiration.
遥か遠く世界超え宇宙まで
Far beyond the world, even to the cosmos,
この想い果てしなく届けたい
I want to deliver these endless feelings.
オリエンタル オクシデンタル
Oriental, Occidental,
どちらも愛しちゃって
I love them both!
掻き立てる衝動が加速する
The stirring impulse accelerates,
創造の世界へと飛び込んで
plunging into the world of creation.
小噺に乗せて
Set to a short story,
寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
Roll up, roll up! Come closer and see!
語り継いでいく
We will pass down...
人世の想い
...the thoughts of our human lifetime,
あなたの心に
staying close...
寄り添って
...to your heart.
道楽主義で
With a philosophy of hobbyism,
小粋にいなせ
chic and stylish,
そんな生き様
such a way of life,
如何ですか？
how does it suit you?
遥か遠く電波に乗って
Far away, riding the airwaves,
あなたまで
all the way to you.
この想い純粋に伝えたい
I want to convey these feelings purely.
新しい世界見せてあげる
I will show you a brand new world.
開口一番 ひょっとして
First thing out of my mouth, could it be...
破天荒に型破って打ち立てる
Breaking the mold in an unprecedented way, establishing...
金字塔 パンチライン 時を超え
...a monumental punchline across time!
出囃子に乗せて
Set to the theatrical entrance music,
寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
Roll up, roll up! Come closer and see!
寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい！
Come closer and see!
はい、はい！
Yeah, yeah!
はい！
Yeah!
はい、はい！
Yeah, yeah!
はい！ということで
All right! And with that...
ということで、始まりました！
With that, it has finally begun!
儒烏風亭らでん新衣装
Juufutei Raden's new outfit...
お披露目ライブー！
...debut live show!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much!
はい、皆様改めまして、こんばんは！
Alright, everyone, once again, good evening!
ホロライブデバイス、ReGLOSSの、神出鬼没のミュージアムプリンセス担当！
From hololive DEV_IS, ReGLOSS's elusive museum princess,
儒烏風亭一門は、前座見習い！
and the apprentice storyteller of the Juufutei family,
ちょっと待って、あはは！
Hold on a second, haha!
儒烏風亭らでんでございます！
I am Juufutei Raden!
みんな来てくれて、ありがとうございます！
Thank you all so much for coming!
本日のハッシュタグは、ハッシュタグ...
Today's hashtag is, hashtag...
「らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ」
#RadenNewOutfitDebut3DLive
で、いっぱいポストしてくれると、とっても嬉しいです。よろしくお願いします！
I'd be so happy if you post a lot using it. Thank you!
ちょっと待って、「大丈夫？」って言われてます。大丈夫、大丈夫です！ありがとうございます！
Hold on, people are asking if I'm okay. I'm okay, really! Thank you!
はい！
Alright!
さあ、今回ね、らでん3D、あ、お披露目ライブ...
So this time, Raden's 3D— I mean, Debut Live...
新衣装お披露目ライブ、ミラクル重大発表祭り！
New Outfit Debut Live: Miracle Major Announcement Festival!
タイトルにもある通り、何やら重大発表が...
Just as the title says, there are some major announcements...
あるとか、ないとか...結構色々ね。
...whether you believe it or not.
しかも、1つだけじゃないの！
And what's more, it's not just one!
うわーーー！
Whoa!
ということで、今日はね、ぜひ
So today, please make sure...
最後までお楽しみください！
...to enjoy the show until the very end!
はい！
Yes!
さあ、そして皆様、気になってますよね？|さあ、そして皆様、気になってますよね？
Now, everyone, you're curious, aren't you?
この新衣装、いかがですか？
What do you think of this new outfit?
でんでんでんでんでんでんでん
*Drumroll sounds*
どう？みんな、どうかな？
How is it? Everyone, what do you think?
これが私、らでんの新衣装、ミュージアムプリンセス衣装でーす！
This is my new outfit, the Museum Princess outfit!
どう？どうかな？どうかな？みんな
How is it? How do you like it, everyone?
ちょっとね、今日ね、コメントとのラグがあってあれなんですけれども、
There's a bit of a lag with the chat comments today, but...
「良い」「良い」！ありがとう！
You like it? Thank you!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much!
「可愛い」「可愛い」！ありがとうございます！
'Cute! Cute!' Thank you so much!
えー、今回ですね、100万人記念ということで、
So, this is to celebrate reaching 1 million subscribers,
さくらしおり先生にお仕立ていただきました！
and it was designed by Sakura Shiori-sensei!
イェーイ！
Yay!
これもね、普段から応援してくださっている皆様のおかげです。
This is all thanks to everyone who always supports me.
本当にありがとう！
Thank you so, so much!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you!
もちろんね、このライブの後、
Of course, after this live show,
アンコールライブっていうのがメンバー限定であるんですけれども、
there's an encore stream for members only,
そこでまた、のんびりと、このお衣装について詳しく見ていきたいと思いますので、
where I want to take a closer, more relaxed look at this outfit.
思って、という方はぜひ、メンバーシップの方に加入していただければと思います。
If you'd like, please consider joining my membership.
今日ね、お昼くらいに、メンバーの方が使えるスタンプを追加されましたので、ぜひコメント欄で、よかったら使ってみてください。
We added new member emotes around noon today, so please feel free to use them in the chat!
もうみんな使いたくてたまらないアロワナスタンプとかが追加されてるんで、ぜひみなさんでね、コメント欄いっぱいアロワナを泳がせてください。よろしくお願いします。
We've got those Arowana emotes everyone's been dying to use. Let's flood the chat with swimming Arowanas! Thank you!
さあ、ということで。お衣装、改めて、新衣装なんですが。
And with that... Here is my new outfit once again.
今回お衣装の他に、ちょっとね、ひとつ、とあるものを、作りましたよ。
Besides the outfit, I also had something else made!
ま、楽曲中にもね、出てきたんですけれども。
It actually appeared during the song earlier...
じゃんじゃかじゃんじゃんじゃん、あ、逆、あ、じゃん！
Ta-da! Ah, wait, it's upside down... Ta-da!
ステッキでございます！
It's a wand!
いいでしょう、これ。かっこいいでしょう？今回ね、特注でステッキ、作っちゃった！
Isn't it great? It looks so cool, right? I had this wand custom-made!
しかも、これだけじゃないんですよ。
And that's not all!
見ててね。
Watch this.
ラデン、ビーム！
Raden Beam!
うわー！レーザービームだ！すごい！
Whoa! It's a laser beam! Incredible!
今回ね、あの、レーザービームを出せるようにしてもらいました。
I had them make it so it can shoot a laser beam.
ヴン、ヴン、ヴン、ヴン、ヴン、ヴン！
Vroom, vroom, vroom, vroom, vroom, vroom!
もう大丈夫です。
Okay, that's enough.
いかん、もう今日はね、ライブ、まだまだこれからですので、体力は温存していかないと。
Oh dear, the concert has only just begun, so I need to save my energy.
でも今日は、自分の体力が、もう空っぽになるまで、全力でライブするから、みんな応援よろしくね！
But today, I'm going to perform with everything I've got until I'm completely drained, so please cheer me on!
それでは、そろそろ、次の曲に行きたいと思います。
Now, it's about time we move on to the next song.
さ、次の曲はなんなのか、重大発表はなんなのか、ワクワクしながら聞いてくださいね。
Look forward to what the next song and the big announcement will be!
そしてここからはゲストも登場します！
And we have guests joining us from here on!
ゲストパートは収録になりますので、あしからず。
Please note that the guest segment is pre-recorded.
それでは、今宵はまだまだ始まったばかり。みんなで一緒に楽しみましょう。
Tonight is still young. Let's enjoy it together!
それでは、どうぞ！
Now, please enjoy!
そう高く 果てなく
So high, endlessly
明日へと 導くよ
Leading to tomorrow
私だけの光 放ちたい
I want to release my own light
DIVE!
WOW WOW WOW
自信なくしてたんだ 心に鍵かけて
I just lost my confidence and locked my heart
響く自分の声に 耳塞いでた
I was covering my ears to the sound of my own voice
本当は いつだって わかっていたんだよ
Honestly, I knew all along
さあ 出会いが この瞬間 彩るよ
Come, our meeting colors this moment
私だけの光 信じて
Believing in my own light,
DIVE!
空高く
High in the sky,
果てなく
endlessly,
抱きしめた未来が 奇跡になる
The future we embraced will become a miracle
生まれた
The newborn
思いが
feelings
明日へと導くよ
will lead us to tomorrow.
私だけの光 放ちたい
I want to radiate my own light,
DIVE!
Wow wow wow
JAPANの美術史 (アート！アート！)
JAPAN's Art History (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史 (絵画に立体！)
JAPAN's Art History (Paintings and sculptures!)
JAPANの美術史 (テストもバッチリ！)
JAPAN's Art History (Tests are a breeze!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！
O-bo-e-ma-SHOW!
さあ、3Dライブの途中ではございますが
Now, although we are in the middle of a 3D live...
ここで日本美術史の授業を始めたいと思います！
...I would like to start a Japanese art history class here!
はーい、みなさんこんにちは！美術史を学ぶ時間です！
Hello, everyone! It's time to learn art history!
まずは縄文、弥生、古墳まで、やってみよう！
First, let's try the Jomon, Yayoi, and Kofun periods!
火焔型土器、遮光器土偶、縄文のビーナス！
Flame-style vessels, goggle-eyed clay figurines, and the Venus of Jomon!
銅鐸、銅戈、銅矛、銅剣、弥生土器！
Bronze bells, daggers, spears, swords, and Yayoi pottery!
埴輪も色々、踊る人々、挂甲武人、馬形埴輪！
Various clay figures, dancing people, armed warriors, and horse-shaped Haniwa!
古墳出土の鉄刀、鉄剣、七支刀に、土師器、須恵器！
Iron daggers and swords from tombs, the Seven-Branched Sword, Hajiki and Sueki wares!
OK OK OK OK いい感じ！
OK, OK, OK, OK, looking good!
次は飛鳥に奈良時代、3、2、1、Go！
Next is the Asuka and Nara periods! 3, 2, 1, Go!
仏像いっぱい釈迦如来、菩薩と合わせて三尊像！
Lots of Buddhist statues like Shakyamuni, and the Triad with Bodhisattvas!
玉虫厨子、天寿国繍帳、金堂壁画、古墳壁画！
Tamamushi Shrine, Tenjukoku Shucho tapestry, Golden Hall murals, and tomb murals!
東大寺には奈良の大仏、興福寺には阿修羅像！
The Great Buddha at Todaiji, and the Ashura statue at Kofukuji!
音と一緒に遊びましょう！螺鈿紫檀五絃琵琶！
Let's play along with the sound! The five-string lute with mother-of-pearl inlay!
未来のキミに届くように
So that it reaches you in the future,
繋いでいこう この想い
let's pass on these feelings.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there's love, we'll be fine,
語り合おう 朝が来るまで
let's talk until morning comes.
JAPANの美術史 (アート！アート！)
JAPAN's Art History (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史 (絵画に立体！)
JAPAN's Art History (Paintings and sculptures!)
JAPANの美術史 (テストもバッチリ！)
JAPAN's Art History (Tests are a breeze!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！
O-bo-e-ma-SHOW!
まだまだ色々ございます、がんばってついてきてくださいね
There is still much more to come, so do your best to keep up!
平安、鎌倉、南北朝...参る！
Heian, Kamakura, Nanbokucho periods... Here we go!
曼荼羅、一木造り、寄木造り！
Mandalas, single-wood carving, and joint-block carving!
鳥獣人物戯画に、源氏物語！
Scrolls of Frolicking Animals and Humans, and The Tale of Genji!
平等院鳳凰堂阿弥陀如来坐像！
The seated Amida Nyorai statue of Byodoin Phoenix Hall!
模様がとってもかわいい、片輪車螺鈿手箱！
With a very cute pattern, the mother-of-pearl cosmetic box!
東大寺の南大門の金剛力士像！
The Kongo Rikishi statues at the Nandaimon of Todaiji!
阿弥陀二十五菩薩来迎図、山越阿弥陀図！
Descent of Amida and the Twenty-Five Bodhisattvas, and Amida Rising over Hills!
蒙古襲来絵詞、空也上人像！
The Illustrated Account of the Mongol Invasions, and the statue of Priest Kuya!
一遍上人絵伝、後三年合戦絵巻！
Illustrated Biography of Priest Ippen, and Scrolls of the Three Years' War!
YOYO！半分くらい来たぜ多分！
Yo, yo! We're probably about halfway through!
まだまだいくぜ、ありのまま、室町から安土桃山！
Still going, keeping it real, from Muromachi to Azuchi-Momoyama!
能面「翁」に、枯山水！
The Noh mask 'Okina' and dry landscape gardens!
天橋立図、呂洞賓図！
View of Amanohashidate, and Lu Dongbin!
狩野派の屏風！
Folding screens of the Kano School!
曜変天目茶碗！
The Yohen Tenmoku tea bowl!
洛中洛外図屏風！
Scenes in and around Kyoto folding screens!
唐獅子図屏風、松鷹図！
Chinese Lions folding screen, and Pine Tree and Hawk!
職人尽図、花下遊楽図！
Scroll of Various Craftsmen, and Amusements Under the Blossoms!
松林図、山水図、八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱、本物だーー！
Pine Trees screen, Landscapes, and the Yatsuhashi Writing Box with Iris... It's the real one!
未来のキミに届くように
So that it reaches you in the future,
繋いでいこう この想い
let's pass on these feelings.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there's love, we'll be fine,
語り合おう 朝が来るまで
let's talk until morning comes.
なんと今回、特別にバーチャル八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱様に来ていただきました！
For this special occasion, the Virtual Yatsuhashi Writing Box has joined us!
ありがとうございました！
Thank you very much!
あとちょっと、最後までがんばろう！
Just a bit more, let's do our best until the end!
江戸時代から昭和まで、いくよ！
From the Edo period to the Showa period, here we go!
3、2、1、Go！
3, 2, 1, Go!
舟橋蒔絵硯箱、風神雷神図屏風！
Writing Box with Pontoon Bridge, and Wind and Thunder Gods screens!
燕子花図屏風、見返り美人！
Irises screen, and Beauty Looking Back!
好色一代男、奥の細道...
The Life of an Amorous Man, and The Narrow Road to the Deep North...
好色一代男、奥の細道
The Life of an Amorous Man, The Narrow Road to the Deep North
富嶽三十六景
Thirty-Six Views of Mount Fuji
東海道中膝栗毛
Tokaido Road on Foot
老猿、ゆあみ、こん
Old Monkey, Bathing, Spirit Fox
墓守、伎芸天
Gravekeeper, Gigeiten
竜虎図、黒き猫
Dragon and Tiger, Black Cat
鮭、海の幸
Salmon, Bounty of the Sea
渡頭の夕暮
Twilight at the Ferry Crossing
麗子微笑、紫禁城
Reiko Smiling, Forbidden City
斑猫、五浦釣人
Tabby Cat, Angler of Izura
太陽の塔
Tower of the Sun
吉原治良の円
Jiro Yoshihara's Circle
東山魁夷の道
Road by Kaii Higashiyama
未来のキミに届くように
To reach the future you
繋いでいこう、この想い
Let's connect these thoughts
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there is love, it's okay
語り合おう、朝が来るまで
Let's talk until the morning comes
未来まで
To the future
JAPANの美術史 (アート！アート！)
History of Japanese Art (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史 (絵画に立体！)
History of Japanese Art (Paintings and sculptures!)
JAPANの美術史 (テストもバッチリ！)
History of Japanese Art (Even the test is perfect!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！ありがとう！
Let's memorize it! Thank you!
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、
To everyone watching the live stream,
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここで、らでの小話、美術解説のお時間です！
We're in the middle of the live, but now it's time for Raden's art talk commentary!
なんと、今回ご紹介するのは、こちらでーす！じゃじゃーん！
And what we are introducing this time is this! Ta-dah!
国宝『八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱』ということで、
The National Treasure, 'Eight-Bridge Inkstone Box with Mother-of-Pearl Inlay'!
今回、特別に東京国立博物館さんから3Dモデルをお借りしましたー！
This time, we specially borrowed a 3D model from the Tokyo National Museum!
いよっ、皆にもよく見てもらいましょう。こちらでございます！
Alright, let's take a close look. Here it is!
こちらが、バーチャル『八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱』です！らでんってなんかどっかで聞いたことがありますね。
This is the virtual 'Eight-Bridge Inkstone Box with Mother-of-Pearl Inlay'! 'Raden' sounds familiar.
なんか、そんな名前のバーチャルYouTuberがいるような、いないような。
Like there's a Virtual YouTuber with that name, or maybe not.
こちらは、私のオリジナル曲『JAPANの美術史 お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW!』にも登場する作品です。
This piece also appears in my original song, 'JAPAN's Art History: Let's Memorize It!'
どうですか、皆さん、この輝きとデザイン！
How do you like this shine and design, everyone?
大胆かつ、花びらの装飾の細かい部分も美しいこちらの作品、
This piece is bold yet beautiful down to the detailed flower petal decorations.
作ったのは、尾形光琳という人です。
It was made by a person named Ogata Korin.
彼がこの硯箱を作ったのは江戸時代なんですが、どこかモダンな要素も感じることができます。
He made this inkstone box in the Edo period, but you can feel some modern elements in it.
さて、工芸品を見る時、様々な見方がありますが、手助けになるのは作品名です。ではスライドいきます。
There are various ways to view crafts, but the artwork's name helps. Let's move to the slide.
この工芸品の名前を復習しましょう。『八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱』。
Let's review the name of this craft: 'Eight-Bridge Inkstone Box with Mother-of-Pearl Inlay'.
漢字がたくさん入っていますが、一つ一つ紐解いていきます。
It has many kanji characters, but let's break them down one by one.
まずは、「八橋」。
First, 'Yatsuhashi' (Eight Bridges).
日本美術史における工芸品は、物語の一場面や、和歌、歌ですね、がテーマになっていることが少なくありません。
Crafts in Japanese art history are often themed around a scene from a story or a waka (poem).
そして、この硯箱もその一つ。
And this inkstone box is one of them.
『伊勢物語』第九段「三河国八橋」の場面が主題になっているんですよ。なので、これは橋ですね。
The theme is based on the scene of 'Yatsuhashi in Mikawa Province' from Section 9 of 'The Tales of Ise'. So, this is a bridge.
八橋、この場面に出てくる8つの橋のこと。つまりは、何を描いたかを表しています。
The 'Eight Bridges' refer to the eight bridges in this scene. In short, it shows what is depicted.
では、何を描いたかが分かったら、次に、どんな技法が使われたか。
Once we know what is depicted, next is what kind of technique was used.
それを表すのが、蒔絵、そして螺鈿です。
That is represented by 'Makie' and 'Raden' (Mother-of-Pearl).
蒔絵とは簡単に言うと、金などの粉を漆という接着剤を用いて貼り付けたもの。
Simply put, 'Makie' is gold powder sprinkled on wet lacquer, which acts as an adhesive.
ここで言うと、カキツバタの葉っぱの部分ですね。ピョンピョンってなってる部分です。
In this case, it's the leaves of the iris flowers. The spiky parts.
次に、螺鈿とは、貝がらの光沢のある部分を薄く剥がして貼り付けたもの。
Next, 'Raden' is when the lustrous part of a seashell is thinly peeled and inlaid.
ここで言うと、カキツバタのお花の部分です。
Here, it's the flower petals of the irises.
この作品に使われているのはアワビ貝で、花びらを表現するために、あえて穴の空いた貝を使用しているのが分かります。
Abalone shells are used. You can see she intentionally chose shells with natural holes to represent the petals.
そして最後に、そもそもこれは何か。
And finally, what actually is this object?
それを表すのが、「硯箱」です。
That is represented by 'Suzuribako' (Inkstone Box).
真ん中をご覧ください。こちら、墨汁を作る、硯入れが上の段にあり、
Look at the center. The upper tier holds the inkstone used to make ink,
さらにその段の下、下の段は、料紙、紙入れになっています。
and the lower tier is designed as a paper container.
さあ、これで「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」の言葉の紐解きが完了しましたね。
Now, we have successfully broken down the name 'Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako'.
カキツバタが咲く、川にかかる橋のダイナミックな魅力にも大注目なこの硯箱。
Pay close attention to the dynamic charm of the bridge over the river with blooming irises.
パカッと開けると、波が描かれています。
When you open it up, waves are depicted inside.
もうここまで聞いたら、なぜそこに波の意匠を施したのか、皆様ならお分かりですね。
Now that you've heard all this, I'm sure you understand why she put a wave design there.
の上にある橋の下の波、ということですね。
These are the waves beneath the bridge on the level...
実はですね、こちらの八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱、
Actually, this Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Suzuribako...
普段展示される際は、箱を閉じた状態なんですよ。
...is usually displayed in a closed state.
つまり、中の様子をご覧いただけるのは、この配信ならではの貴重な機会です！
Meaning, seeing inside is a precious opportunity exclusive to this stream!
こちらがなんと、2026年5月26日から8月16日、本館2室にて展示されるとのことで、
Incredibly, this will be exhibited in Room 2 of the Main Building from May 26 to August 16, 2026.
東京国立博物館さんで、ぜひ見てみていただければと思います！
So I hope you'll go see it at the Tokyo National Museum!
このね、波の細かいところがね、これ筆でやってますからね、筆でこうやって...
Look at the fine details of these waves—this was done with a brush! Like this...
あ、お時間となってしまいました。
Oh, looks like our time is up.
それでは皆さん、また次回お会いいたしましょう。
Well then, everyone, see you next time!
特報 その①
[Special Announcement Part 1]
儒烏風亭らでん x 東京国立博物館
[Juufutei Raden x Tokyo National Museum]
未来の君に届くように
To reach you in the future...
繋いでいこう この思い
Let's connect these feelings...
愛し合えれば 大丈夫
As long as we love each other, we'll be fine.
語り合おう 朝が来るまで
Let's talk to each other until morning comes.
ということでなんと！私、儒烏風亭らでんと！
And so, incredibly! I, Juufutei Raden...
東京国立博物館さんとのコラボが決定しました！
...and the Tokyo National Museum are officially collaborating!
すごい！みんなやったよ！
This is amazing! We did it, everyone!
もうね、らでん配信とか色んなところで、東博さんがね、ずっと大好きだって言ってたんですけれども、
I've constantly expressed my deep love for Tohaku in my streams and elsewhere, but...
今回ね、念願の！東博・らでんコラボでございます！すごい！
now, my long-awaited Tohaku-Raden collab is finally happening! This is incredible!
あら？東博、最近名前聞きましたね。
Oh? Have you heard that name recently?
そうです。先日ね、10月から京都、1月から東京にて開催予定の特別展、
That right! It was recently announced that...
「源氏物語 王朝のかがやき」展の音声ガイドのスペシャルトラックを務めさせていただくことが発表されましたが、
...I will record a special track for the audio guide of 'The Tale of Genji' exhibition!
なんと、この特別展「源氏物語」展の東京会場となる、東京国立博物館さんとも...
And amazingly, with the Tokyo National Museum, which is the Tokyo venue for the exhibition...
コラボが決定いたしました！すごーい！
...a collaboration has officially been decided! Incredible!
開催時期は、この「源氏物語」展と同じ、2027年1月に実施予定となっております！
It's scheduled for January 2027, aligning with the Tokyo run of 'The Tale of Genji' exhibition!
なんで、こっちは「源氏物語」展・儒烏風亭らでんコラボ、そして同じ1月に、
So on one hand, we have 'The Tale of Genji' exhibition collab, and in that same January...
東京国立博物館・儒烏風亭らでんコラボがあると！
we'll also have a Tokyo National Museum x Juufutei Raden collaboration!
もっと簡単に言うと、来年の1月は東博のいろんなところにらでんちゃんが出没しちゃいます！っていう感じです！
To put it simply, Raden will be popping up all over Tohaku next January!
こちら、詳細はですね、また続報をお待ちいただければと思います！
Please stay tuned for more details in future announcements!
すごいでしょう？すごい、すごい！
Isn't that amazing? It's so, so cool!
ということで、本日の重大発表1つ目は、東博・儒烏風亭らでんコラボでございました！みんなありがとう！
So, today's first major announcement was the Tohaku x Juufutei Raden collab! Thank you, everyone!
さあ、ライブも重大発表もまだまだ続きます。ちょっと待って、ちょっと疲れちゃった。
The live stream and major announcements aren't over yet. Hang on... I'm a little out of breath!
ということでね、東博、もともとらでんが日本美術史に興味持ったのって、東博さんで能面を見て、
Actually, my interest in Japanese art history began when I saw a Noh mask at Tohaku.
その時に、「あ、なんて美しいんだ！」って思ったし、
At that moment, I thought, 'Oh, how beautiful!'
「らでんって日本で生まれ育ったのに日本のこと本当に何も知らないんだな」って思ったのがきっかけで、
and realized I knew nothing about Japan despite being born and raised here.
そこから、何やかんやあって日本美術史を勉強したりして、
That sparked my journey to study Japanese art history...
何やかんやあってホロライブに入って、何やかんやあって今こんな素敵な衣装をお披露目して、
...which somehow led me to Hololive, debuting this beautiful outfit today...
何やかんやあって、こんなありがたいコラボをさせていただけることになりました！みんなのおかげだよ！ありがとう！...
...and somehow, getting this dream collaboration! It's all thanks to you!
もう人生本当に何が起こるか分かりません。
You really never know what life has in store for you.
何がどう未来へ繋がっていくのかみたいなことも分かりません。人生は奇妙な冒険みたいなものでございますな。
You can't predict how things connect to the future. Life is like a bizarre adventure.
さあ、ということでそろそろ次の曲に行きたいと思います。
With that said, it's about time to move on to the next song.
それでは聞いてください、「ココロパズルリズム」
Please listen to: 'Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm'.
[ココロパズルリズム]
[Song: Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm]
Ah...
ココロのパズル
The puzzle of the heart...
ココロのリズム
The rhythm of the heart...
ココロのパズル
The puzzle of the heart...
ココロのリズム
The rhythm of the heart...
これからの未来
As for the future from now on,
ほらたくさんのピース
look, there are so many pieces.
組み立てるのはキミしだい
Deciding how to assemble them is up to you.
一つずつの明日を生きる
One by one, living for tomorrow,
ココロのパズルとリズム
this is the puzzle and rhythm of the heart.
うまくは言えないけど
I can't say it well, but
不思議と安心して
it feels strangely reassuring
いられる感覚って
to have this feeling of being able to be here,
まるでパズルみたいだ
it's just like a puzzle.
もうずっと前から
We've had reserved seats
僕らは予約席
since long, long ago.
さあ 両手つないで
Come on, let's hold hands,
きっと一つになれる
we'll surely become one.
完成が見えていても
Even if we can see the completion,
すんなりとはいかないね
it doesn't go smoothly, does it?
それぞれが夢のカケラだね
Each of us is a piece of a dream, right?
これからの未来
As for the future from now on,
ほらたくさんのピース
look, there are so many pieces.
組み立てるのはキミしだい
Deciding how to assemble them is up to you.
一つずつの明日を生きる
One by one, living for tomorrow,
空いた隙間を埋める
filling the empty gaps.
楽しいこともきっとあるけど
There will surely be fun things, too, but
それよりも大切なのは
more important than that is,
悲しかったり嬉しいときに
when we're sad or when we're happy,
一緒に泣けるそんなココロのパズル
being able to cry together, that is the heart's puzzle.
すんなりとはいかないね
It doesn't go smoothly, does it?
キミと僕のパズルの行方も
The destination of the puzzle of you and me...
これからのLove Story
As for the love story from now on,
ほらたくさんのピース
look, there are so many pieces.
間違えることもあるけど
Even if we make mistakes sometimes,
あ、こちらで！
Ah, this way!
じゃじゃーん！
Tada!
クロード・モネ『睡蓮の池』
Claude Monet, "The Water-Lily Pond"
今回なんと、ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんより画像をお借りしております！本当にありがとうございます！
This time, believe it or not, we have borrowed this image from the National Gallery in London! Thank you so much!
皆さん、どうですか？
Everyone, what do you think?
私、モネの描く世界が大好きなんです。
I absolutely love the world that Monet paints.
まあ、モネといえば日本でもとても人気の高い画家ですが、彼の絵画の魅力はどのようなところにあるのでしょうか。
Well, Monet is a very popular painter in Japan, but what exactly is the charm of his paintings?
今回は、彼の絵画に内在する魅力を言語化していきましょう！
This time, let's put the inherent appeal of his paintings into words!
この作品は、1899年頃に描かれました。
This artwork was painted around 1899.
緑色の光が溢れる睡蓮の池には、大きな橋が架かり、橋の奥には、柳が描かれています。
Over the water-lily pond filled with green light, a large bridge is built, and behind the bridge, willows are painted.
実はこの場所、モネの自宅に作った池なんです。
Actually, this place is a pond that Monet built at his own home.
フランスのジヴェルニーという街に家を購入した彼は、近隣の川から水を引き、自分の理想とする庭を作りました。
After purchasing a house in the town of Giverny, France, he drew water from a neighboring river to create his ideal garden.
アーチ状の大きな橋、これ、いわゆる「太鼓橋」と呼ばれる橋と、柳。
An arched large bridge. This is what you would call a "taikobashi" (drum bridge). And willows.
あれ？なんだか日本ぽさを感じませんか？
Huh? Don't you feel some Japanese influence there?
それもそのはず。彼は日本の浮世絵に強く影響を受けた画家でした。
And for good reason. He was a painter strongly influenced by Japanese ukiyo-e woodblock prints.
彼の描く絵は、光に溢れていて、目の前で風が吹いて、水面が揺れているようにも見えます。
His paintings are filled with light, making it look as if the wind is blowing right before your eyes, and the water surface is rippling.
じーっと見ていると、水も花も木も、橋も、空気でさえも溶けていくようです。
If you look closely, the water, flowers, trees, bridge, and even the air seem to melt together.
見ていて落ち着く絵画だと思いませんか？
Don't you think it's a painting that brings peace of mind just by looking at it?
モネは絵を描くとき、色を混ぜて塗るのではなく、純粋な、何も混ざっていない色を置くように塗りました。
When painting, Monet didn't mix colors to apply them; instead, he applied pure, unmixed colors as if placing them on the canvas.
色は混ぜれば混ぜるほど、塗り重ねれば重ねるほど、暗くなっていきます。
The more you mix colors, and the more you layer them, the darker they become.
彼はこの課題を「色を置く」ことによって解決し、光に溢れた絵画の表現に成功したんです。
He solved this issue by "placing colors," succeeding in creating a painting expression filled with light.
この絵画に近づいてみると、筆跡がしっかり残っています。
If you get close to this painting, you can clearly see the brushstrokes left behind.
隣り合った絵の具、一つ一つの相乗効果を計算し、絵の具の塊から、温度感や湿度感を感じることができる風景へと変貌する表現は、モネが生涯かけて研究していたものです。
By calculating the synergistic effect of each adjacent paint stroke, the expression that transforms a mass of paint into a landscape where you can feel the warmth and humidity was something Monet researched throughout his life.
光を求めたモネが、陰影のない日本の浮世絵に強く惹かれたのも納得がいきますね。
It makes sense that Monet, in his pursuit of light, was strongly drawn to Japanese ukiyo-e, which lacks shading.
彼の絵画の明るさは、画家としての研究の成果であり、情熱さえ感じられるそんな作品だと私は感じます。
I feel that the brightness of his paintings is the result of his research as an artist, a work where you can truly feel his passion.
みんなはこの絵画、どう読んだかな？
How did everyone interpret this painting?
実はモネは、「印象派」の画家と呼ばれるきっかけを作った人でもあるんですが、それはまた別のお話。
Actually, Monet is also the one who triggered the naming of the "Impressionists," but that's a story for another time.
という感じでございました。こちらはロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんにて見ることができます。ぜひ行ってみてください！
And that's about it. You can see this at the National Gallery in London. Please do go see it!
また次回！
See you next time!
I want to fight your brother.
Let's kung-fu!
Every night I look to the skies and wonder what we did
Always a naive point of view that breaks us in the end
If I could find the meaning of it all I'd take the chance
Maybe in time we'll walk the mile and change it if we can
It's now and always (How did we get this far)
Always (We're making a brand new start)
Always (Nothing will hold me down)
Always (Wave goodbye to me!)
Around the world 新しいことに
Around the world, to new things
Around the world 踏み出す力で
Around the world, with the power to take a step forward
Around the world 世界は変わるさ
Around the world, the world will change
But don't run away 'cause if it's not OK!
I'll change that world into something better, honey!
Let's kung-fu!
果てしなく広がる...
Endlessly spreading...
果てしなく広がるこの大地を僕らはまた歩き続けるさ
We'll walk the mile again across this endlessly spreading earth
全ての意味が分かるのならば
If we could find the meaning of it all
この瞳で何を見つめるのだろう
What would we look at with these eyes?
It's now and always (How did we get this far na~)
It's now and always (How did we get this far)
Always (We're making a brand new start na~)
Always (We're making a brand new start)
Always (Nothing will hold me down na~)
Always (Nothing will hold me down)
Always, wave goodbye to me!
Around the world 君だけのために
Around the world, for you and you alone
Around the world 探し続けるよ
Around the world, I'll keep searching
Around the world 奇跡のかけらを
Around the world, for the pieces of miracles
But don't run away 'cause if it's not OK!
Yeah ey, and you know it's gonna be raining
And you know it's gonna be hard
As long as we trust each other
Nothing's gonna break us apart oh no no!
If ya wanna be somebody, get up on ya feet and go
I know we're gonna meet each other somewhere around the globe
Around the world いつでも自分に
Around the world, those who always lose...
Around the world 負けている人は
Around the world, ...to themselves...
Around the world 何も掴めない
Around the world, ...can grasp nothing at all
But don't run away 'cause if it's not OK!
I'll change that world into something better honey!
特報 その②
Special Announcement Part 2
儒烏風亭らでん × THE NATIONAL GALLERY LONDON
Juufuutei Raden × THE NATIONAL GALLERY LONDON
儒烏風亭らでん ロンドン ナショナル・ギャラリー コラボ決定!!
Juufuutei Raden & The National Gallery, London Collab Confirmed!!
「儒烏風亭らでんの瞳に映る世界の名画 ～A Shared Art Journey～」
"World-famous Masterpieces Reflected in Juufuutei Raden's Eyes ~A Shared Art Journey~"
5/20(水) 12:00よりグッズの予約販売が開始
Merchandise pre-orders start from May 20th (Wed) at 12:00
コラボグッズ一覧
Collaboration Merchandise List
はい！ということで、なんと！
Yes! And so, guess what!
私、儒烏風亭らでんと...
I, Juufuutei Raden, and...
ロンドン ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボが決定しましたー！
...have a confirmed collaboration with the National Gallery, London!
ナショナル・ギャラリーさんといえば、もうね、ゴッホ、ターナー...
Speaking of the National Gallery, they have Van Gogh, Turner...
もうとにかく色んな画家さんたちの超有名な作品をいっぱい所蔵されているところなんですが...
...and anyway, they house tons of super famous works by all kinds of painters!
なんと、そんなナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボ、
And guess what, a collaboration with that very National Gallery,
「儒烏風亭らでんの瞳に映る世界の名画 ～A Shared Art Journey～」コラボ決定です！すごーい！
"World-famous Masterpieces Reflected in Juufuutei Raden's Eyes ~A Shared Art Journey~" is confirmed! Amazing!
さあ、これね、とある3つの名画とコラボしてるんですが、
Now, this is a collaboration with three specific famous paintings,
みんな分かるかな？3つね。3つあるんだけど...
but do you know which ones? Three. There are three of them...
えー、では左から行きましょうか。えー、左。ターナー「雨、蒸気、速度―グレート・ウェスタン鉄道」
Well, shall we go from the left? On the left is Turner's "Rain, Steam, and Speed - The Great Western Railway".
そして真ん中。モネの「睡蓮の池」
And in the middle, Monet's "Water-Lilies".
そして一番右。これは皆さんお分かりでしょう。
And on the far right. Everyone probably knows this one.
ゴッホの「ひまわり」
Van Gogh's "Sunflowers".
そして今回、えー、コラボ商品がございます。全8種類あるんですよ。じゃあ、1つずつね、
And this time, we have collaboration items. There are 8 types in total. Let's introduce them one by one...
ちょっと紹介していきましょう。だん！
...one by one. Ta-da!
えー、まず左上から行きましょうか。まずは「フレグランスミストセット」です！
Let's start from the top left. First is the "Fragrance Mist Set"!
らでんが監修したフレグランスミスト。3点の名画が持つイメージを香りで表現しました。
This fragrance mist was supervised by Raden. I expressed the imagery of the three famous paintings through scents.
本商品はアルコールフリーのフレグランスミストなので、色んな場面に合わせて使用可能です。
This product is an alcohol-free fragrance mist, so you can use it in various situations.
じゃあ、隣行きましょうか。
Now, let's move to the next one.
えー、その隣「ローラーボールペン」。3つの名画のエッセンスと儒烏風亭らでんの家紋を美に融合させたデザインでございます。
Next to it is the "Rollerball Pen". This design beautifully fuses the essence of the three paintings with Juufuutei Raden's family crest.
えー、じゃあ次は...
Alright, next up...
左下「カップ＆ソーサーセット」。描き下ろしイラストからインスピレーションを得た、ボーンチャイン製のカップ＆ソーサーセットでございます。
On the bottom left is the "Cup & Saucer Set". This bone china cup and saucer set was inspired by the newly drawn illustrations.
ソーサーの中心には、儒烏風亭らでんの名前も記載されています。
In the center of the saucer, Juufuutei Raden's name is also written.
最近らでんも紅茶飲めるようになったんで、お揃いにしましょうや。
Lately, Raden has also started drinking tea, so let's match!
えー、そしてその隣が「スカーフ」...
And next to that is the "Scarf"...
新たに描き下ろしたイラスト要素を組み合わせ、ファッション性と実用性を兼ね備えたデザインスカーフでございます！
This design scarf combines newly drawn illustration elements, blending fashion and practicality!
えー、そしてじゃあその隣行こうか！アクリルスタンド！本コラボならではの新衣装を身にまとうアクリルスタンドでございます！
And next to it! An acrylic stand! This acrylic stand features the new outfit unique to this collaboration!
えー、じゃあ右上いきましょう！キャンバスアート！描き下ろしイラストを使用されるキャンバスアートでございます！
Now, let's go to the top right! Canvas art! This canvas art uses the newly drawn illustration!
その下はトートバッグ！表面には本コラボのために描き下ろされたイラスト、裏面には3点の名画のディテールをあしらったデザインの両面仕様となっています！
Below that is the tote bag! The front features an illustration drawn for this collab, and the back is a double-sided design adorned with details from three famous paintings!
そして最後！ランダムクリアカードになります！全6種のランダムクリアカードで、一部のカードには箔押しデジタルサインと、特別メッセージが入っていますよー！
And finally! The random clear cards! There are six types, and some of them include a foiled digital signature and a special message!
グッズ、いいでしょう？どれも素敵でしょう？
The merchandise is great, right? They're all wonderful, aren't they?
そして、さらに！グッズだけではございません！ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボで、音声ガイドも収録させていただきました！すごい！
And furthermore! It's not just merchandise! In collaboration with the National Gallery, London, we've also recorded an audio guide! Amazing!
しかも、こちらね、なんと、らでんの公式チャンネルにてアップする予定でございますが、詳細は後日公開予定となりますので、続報をお待ちください！
What's more, we plan to upload this on Raden's official channel, but details will be announced later, so please look forward to further updates!
と、グッズとガイドと盛りだくさんなんですが、みんな、ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリー、どんなところか... ごめんなさい！
So, there's plenty of merchandise and the guide, but everyone, what kind of place is the National Gallery in London... Sorry!
ちょっと待って。
Wait a second.
ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリー、どんなところか気になりませんか？ロンドンの街並み、見てみたくないですか？
Aren't you curious about what kind of place the National Gallery in London is? Don't you want to see the streets of London?
ということで、なんと！実は！ReGLOSSメンバーでロンドンロケに行ってきました！うおー！
And so! Actually! The ReGLOSS members went on location in London! Whoa!
そのロケの様子はReGLOSSチャンネルなどで後日公開予定となっておりますので、こちらもぜひお楽しみに！
The footage from that trip is scheduled to be released later on the ReGLOSS channel and other platforms, so please look forward to that too!
ということで、重大告知その２は、儒烏風亭らでんと、ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボでございました！ありがとう！
So, major announcement number two was the collaboration between Juufuutei Raden and the National Gallery, London! Thank you!
そして今、えー、スタッフさんの方から、どうやら今、Xで、これXですか？Xでトレンド２位だそうです！すごい！みんなありがとう！
And now, I've heard from the staff that apparently we are currently trending #2 on X! Is this X? #2 on X! Amazing! Thank you, everyone!
大丈夫かな？トレンド２位に入った理由がらでんちゃんの体力が心配です、でめっちゃ入ってたらどうしようかなと。
Is it okay? I wonder if the reason we reached #2 is because everyone is worried about Raden's stamina. What if that's why?
でも今日は、今日はもう体力がすっからかんになって、次の日動けなくなるまで頑張るってらでんは決めたんです！だから今日はみんなもね、いっぱい、いっぱい楽しんでほしいです！どうですか？皆さん、ついてこられてますか？
But today, Raden decided to work hard until my energy is completely drained and I can't move the next day! So today, I want everyone to have tons of fun! How is it? Is everyone keeping up?
あ、待ってくださいね。重大発表、まだあるんです！まだあるんです！これで終わりじゃないんですよ！
Oh, wait a second. There are still more major announcements! There are still more! This isn't the end!
しかも、ライブもまだまだ続きますので、皆さんチャンネルはそのままでいいですよ！
What's more, the live concert will keep going, so keep your eyes on this channel!
では、次の曲に行きたいと思います！それでは、どうぞ！
Now, I'd like to move on to the next song! Here we go!
水面に映った青　眩しく揺れる
The blue reflected on the water's surface sways radiantly
手探りで探してた　足りない私
Groping in the dark, searching for my incomplete self
ゆっくりと動き出した　何万年も前から
Slowly starting to move, since tens of thousands of years ago
この時を約束されていたみたいにほら
Look, as if this very moment had been promised to us
風は歌い　雨は語り
The wind sings, the rain speaks
たどり着くよ　光のすみかへ
We will reach it, the home of light
幾重にも重なってる
Layer upon layer, overlapping
この地球（ほし）の偶然
This planet's coincidences
影の向こう　真実の色
Beyond the shadows, the color of truth
見つけ出すよ　光のすみかを
I'll find it, the home of light
一つでも欠けていたら
If even a single piece were missing
きっと出会えてなかったね
We surely would never have met
飛べぬまま見上げてた　透明な空から
Looking up from the transparent sky, unable to fly
透明な空から
From the transparent sky...
真っ直ぐに差し込んだ
...it shone straight down...
優しい朝陽
...a gentle morning sun.
過ぎた季節が歪（いびつ）に
The past season, irregularly...
削った今という瞬き
...carved this blink of an eye called 'now'.
どこにも同じものはないの
Nowhere is there the same thing.
ほら 生きてる証
Look, it's proof of being alive.
風は歌い
The wind sings,
雨は語り
the rain tells stories.
たどり着くよ
We will reach...
光のすみかへ
...the home of light.
幾重にも重なってる
Layer upon layer, they are piled up.
この地球（ほし）の偶然
In this planet's coincidence.
影の向こう 真実の色
Beyond the shadow, the color of truth.
見つけだすよ
We will find it,
光のすみかを
the home of light.
一つでも
Even if one...
欠けていたら
...were missing...
きっと
...surely...
出会えてなかったね
...we wouldn't have met.
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは。
Good evening to everyone watching the live stream.
ライブの途中ではございますが、
Though we are in the middle of the concert,
ここで、らでのこばなし美術解説のお時間です！
it is now time for Raden's Quick Art Lecture!
今回ご紹介するのはこちら、じゃん！
What I'll be introducing this time is... this! Ta-da!
フィンセント・ファン・ゴッホ『ひまわり』。
Vincent van Gogh's "Sunflowers."
今回、ナショナル・ギャラリーさんより画像をお借りしております。ありがとうございます！
We have borrowed this image from the National Gallery this time. Thank you very much!
ゴッホといえば『ひまわり』というイメージを持っている方も少なくないのではないでしょうか？
Many of you probably associate Van Gogh with "Sunflowers," don't you?
それもそのはず、実はゴッホの描いた『ひまわり』は一つだけじゃないんです。
And for good reason, because Van Gogh actually painted more than just one "Sunflowers."
この世界に失われたものも含めて、7つの『ひまわり』があったんですよ。
There were actually seven "Sunflowers" in this world, including those that have been lost.
さて、では実際に作品をじっくり見てみましょう。
Now, let's take a closer look at the actual artwork.
みんなはどんな感想を持ったかな？
What are your impressions of it?
改めて見てみると、色んなことが見えてきます。
Looking at it again, various details start to appear.
よく見ると、ひまわりの花の向きはバラバラで、花びらも不揃いですね。
If you look closely, the sunflowers face in different directions, and their petals are uneven.
しかし、温かな黄色が画面全体を包み込むことで、どこか生命力が溢れているようにも見えませんか？
However, as the warm yellow envelops the entire canvas, doesn't it seem to overflow with vitality?
ここからはゴッホと黄色、そしてゴッホとひまわりについて紐解いていきましょう。
From here, let's unpack Van Gogh and yellow, as well as Van Gogh and sunflowers.
「太陽は淡い硫黄の輝きを伝達するのだ」という言葉を残しているゴッホは、太陽の光を黄色で表現しました。
Van Gogh, who wrote, "The sun transmits a pale sulfur glow," expressed sunlight through yellow.
そして黄色はゴッホにとって生命力の象徴でもあります。
And yellow also symbolized vitality for Van Gogh.
この絵を描いた時、彼はフランス南部のアルルという街で、
When he painted this picture, he was in the city of Arles in the south of France...
心機一転、画家として仲間と頑張っていこうと意気込んでいました。
...turning over a new leaf and determined to make a fresh start with his fellow painters.
そんな気持ちを黄色に託したのかもしれません。
Perhaps he projected those feelings onto the color yellow.
一方で、この絵のモチーフになっているひまわりについて見てみましょう。
On the other hand, let's look at the sunflower itself, which is the motif of this painting.
ひまわりは太陽に向かって咲きます。
Sunflowers bloom facing the sun.
太陽は西洋美術史において、神を象徴します。
In Western art history, the sun symbolizes God.
それに向かって咲くひまわりは、
The sunflower, blooming towards it,
崇拝、従順、忠誠、そして信仰心や愛を象徴します。
symbolizes adoration, obedience, loyalty, and faith or love.
ここでさらに遠回りして、彼の過去について知っていきましょう。
Let's take a further detour and look into his past.
先ほどゴッホがアルルでの生活を始めた時、私は「心機一転」という表現をしました。
Earlier, when Van Gogh started his life in Arles, I used the phrase "turning over a new leaf."
実は彼、元々は牧師さんになりたかったんです。
Actually, he originally wanted to become a pastor.
彼は頑張って勉強や奉仕活動に注力しますが、うまく行きませんでした。
He worked hard, focusing on studies and missionary work, but it didn't go well.
画家の転身は牧師さんへの道を絶たれた後のことだったんですね。
His transition to becoming a painter happened after his path to becoming a pastor was cut off.
そんな彼が描く信仰の象徴であるひまわり。
And so, he painted sunflowers, which are a symbol of faith.
皆様はどう読み解きますか？
How do you interpret this?
未来への希望の光？それとも自分への失望？
A light of hope for the future? Or disappointment in himself?
ゴッホの見た「光 of すみか」はひまわりの中にあったのかもしれませんね。
Perhaps Van Gogh's "home of light" was inside the sunflowers.
という感じでございまして、こちらもロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんにて...
And that's the story! This piece is also kept at the National Gallery in London...
...見ることができます。ぜひぜひ行ってみてください！
...you can see it. Please do go check it out!
あ、また次回！
Ah, see you next time!
はい、ということで！
Yes, so with that!
早いもので次が最後の曲でございますが...
Time flies, but the next song is going to be our last one...
なんと！儒烏風亭らでん...
And believe it or not, Juufutei Raden...
新曲をリリースしまーす！イェーイ！
will be releasing a brand new song! Yay!
特報、新曲リリース！
Special news: new song release!
タイトルは『Miracle Palette』！
The title is "Miracle Palette"!
はい、こちらですね。
Yes, this one right here.
楽曲リリースなんですが、5月18日の0時00分...
As for the release of the song, it will be on May 18th at midnight...
まあ、なので、今日の日付が変わったタイミングでリリースされます。
so basically, right as the date changes tonight.
5月18日といえば、そう！皆さん大正解、国際博物館の日でございます！
Speaking of May 18th, yes, you guessed it! It's International Museum Day!
そんなね、特別な日にリリース！
So, it will be released on such a special day!
そして、この配信が終わってすぐ、MVですね！
And right after this stream ends, the MV...
なんとミュージックビデオが公開されます！
yes, the music video will be released!
儒烏風亭らでん初のダンスてんこ盛り3D MVとなっております。
It's Juufutei Raden's very first dance-packed 3D MV.
そして、こちら楽曲コンセプトはジャズっぽいね、感じになっております！
The song's concept has a very jazzy vibe to it!
ということで！
And so...
今からは、ライブバージョンの『Miracle Palette』を披露したいと思います！
Now, I'd like to perform the live version of "Miracle Palette"!
ダンサーさん、カモーン！
Dancers, come on in!
うわー！よろしくお願いします！お願いしまーす！
Wow! Thank you so much! Please look after us!
はい！ありがとう、キビキビしてくれて、大変ありがとうございます！
Yes! Thank you, thank you so much for moving so briskly!
では、聴いてください。『Miracle Palette』。
Well then, please listen to "Miracle Palette".
暗がりステージに立つ
Standing on a dark stage...
雨傘を携え
holding an umbrella.
朧に霞む構図
A hazy, misty composition...
印象 儚く
a fleeting impression.
始めましょ 雨粒ドローイング
Let's begin, raindrop drawing.
キャンバスはこの空、この世界
The canvas is this sky, this world.
Hop Hop 飛び回る
Hop, hop, jumping around!
Tap Tap 打ち鳴らす
Tap, tap, beating the rhythm!
Dance Dance ぐるぐる
Dance, dance, spinning round and round!
いざ Show Time
Now, it's showtime!
Ladies and gentlemen, Welcome to our magical show!
スポットライトを浴びて
Basking in the spotlight...
輝きを放つ
emitting a radiant glow.
エンタシスよりプリズム
A prism over entasis...
分光をスタンバイ
spectral light on standby.
この鈍色の空に 七色の橋を架けて見せましょう
Let's build a rainbow bridge across this slate-gray sky!
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Now then, take a very close look!
目に映るもの 今を彩るから常
Because everything in your sight will color the present!
大きな絵筆で描き出す保存
Drawing it out with a giant paintbrush...
大胆なパースの中画
within a bold perspective.
びしょ濡れの舞台は画
The soaking wet stage...
ミラクルなパレット転
is a miraculous palette.
マスカレイドな第二部の開演細
The curtain rises on the masquerade of Act Two.
Shall we dance?無
Shall we dance?
モノトーンから極彩色に中
From monochrome to vivid colors...
アシンメトリーなグラデーションで
with an asymmetrical gradation.流通
夢中になってほしいの風
I want you to be completely captivated...雨
雨雲にマーブリング
marbling the rainclouds.
大きな絵筆で描き出す
Drawing it out with a large paintbrush,
大胆なパースの中
inside a bold perspective.
さあ
Come on,
みんなで大団円 迎えに行こう
let's all go to meet the grand finale.
あぁ
Ah,
びしょ濡れの舞台は
the drenched stage is
ミラクルなパレット
a miracle palette.
おお
Oh...
特報 その③
[Special News Part 3]
新情報
[New Information]
ピクセルミュージアム 箱根探訪編 / 儒烏風亭らでんがご案内！
[DLC: Pixel Museum - Hakone Exploration Chapter, guided by Juufuutei Raden!]
儒烏風亭らでんがご案内！ピクセルミュージアム！
Juufuutei Raden guides you! Pixel Museum!
追加ダウンロードコンテンツ「箱根探訪編」配信決定！
Additional downloadable content "Hakone Exploration Chapter" is confirmed for release!
イベント展示のご案内
Information on event exhibitions!
今回のテーマは…箱根！
This time's theme is... Hakone!
らでん館長の大好きな箱根にまつわる作品をご用意しました！
We have prepared works related to Hakone, which Curator Raden loves!
館内もイベント仕様で、箱根の魅力がたっぷりと詰まっています！
The inside of the museum is also event-themed, packed with the charm of Hakone!
もちろん、解説はフルボイスでお届けしますよ！
Of course, the commentary is delivered in full voice!
儒烏風亭らでんがご案内！ピクセルミュージアム
Juufuutei Raden guides you! Pixel Museum
追加ダウンロードコンテンツ「箱根探訪編」2026年12月配信予定！
Additional downloadable content "Hakone Exploration Chapter" is scheduled for release in December 2026!
ちょっと待っといてねー！
Please wait a little bit!
な、な、なんと！
Wh-wh-what!
昨年6月5日の発売から1年を待たずに、
Without even waiting for a year since its release on June 5th last year...
「儒烏風亭らでんがご案内！ピクセルミュージアム」の追加ダウンロードコンテンツ、
the downloadable content for "Juufuutei Raden Guides You! Pixel Museum,"
「箱根探訪編」の配信が決定しました！
the "Hakone Exploration Chapter," is confirmed for release!
やったーーー！
We did it!
みんながね、いっぱいダウンロードしてくれて、みんながたくさん遊んでくれた
It's all thanks to everyone downloading it and playing it so much...
おかげです！本当にありがとうございます！
Thank you so, so much!
今回の舞台は、皆様おなじみの「箱根」でございます。
Our stage this time is "Hakone," which is familiar to everyone.
えー、前作に引き続き、
Continuing from the previous game...
「箱根ガラスの森美術館」様に加え、
in addition to the "Hakone Venetian Glass Museum,"
今回はなんと！
this time, believe it or not,
「ポーラ美術館」様と、
the "Pola Museum of Art," and
「小田急箱根」様にも！
"Odakyu Hakone" as well
ご協力いただけることとなりました！拍手！
have agreed to cooperate with us! Applause!
えー、館長のプライベートルームもイベント仕様にアップデート！
The Curator's private room is also updated to the event specification!
箱根の魅力マシマシでお届けいたしますよ。いいでしょう？
We will deliver it with even more of Hakone's charm. Isn't that great?
そんな追加ダウンロードコンテンツ「箱根探訪編」は、
This additional downloadable content, "Hakone Exploration Chapter,"
2026年12月に配信予定。
is scheduled for release in December 2026.
早速ですね、来週5月23日、24日に、
First off, next week on May 23rd and 24th,
京都にて開催されます「BitSummit」に、らでぴくも登場！
Radepiku will also appear at "BitSummit" held in Kyoto!
大好評発売中のらでぴくの試遊や、
With playable demos of Radepiku, which is currently on sale to great acclaim,
箱根探訪編のキービジュアルポストカードの配布もあるみたいですよ！
and it seems they will also be distributing key visual postcards of the Hakone Exploration Chapter!
詳しい情報は、公式ホームページとジュピターさんの公式Xを要チェックです。
Be sure to check the official website and Jupiter's official X for detailed information.
まだまだ、嬉しい情報もあるかも？
There might be even more exciting news to come!
それでは、リリースまでお楽しみに！
So, look forward to the release!
はい、そしてそして！皆様お待ちかね！
Yes, and next, and next! What you've all been waiting for!
儒烏風亭らでん、100万人記念グッズが発売されます！
Juufuutei Raden 100-million milestone celebratory goods will be released!
ごめんね、今日本当に何か発表が多くて。
I'm sorry, there are really so many announcements today.
えー、早速詳細見ていきましょう！1つ目は、こちら。デン！
Let's look at the details right away! The first one is this, ta-da!
「新衣装でライブ！アクリルブロック」いや、めっちゃ疲れてるらでんが映っちゃった。
"Live in New Outfit! Acrylic Block"... Oh, a very tired Raden was shown on screen.
ライブステージで楽しそうに歌う新衣装のらでん。もりくらえん先生の描き下ろしでございます。いいでしょう？
Raden in her new outfit singing happily on the live stage. Illustrated by Morikura En-sensei. Isn't it wonderful?
こちらアクリルブロックの表裏に印刷されておりまして、めっちゃね、奥行きが感じられるものとなっておるんですよ。
This is printed on both the front and back of the acrylic block, making it feel incredibly deep.
続いてはこちら。デン！
Next is this. Ta-da!
「らでんの衣装いろいろ 3連結アクリルキーホルダー」
"Raden's Various Outfits 3-Chain Acrylic Keyholder"
新衣装、通常衣装、フラッシュポイント衣装の、3種類の3連結アクリルキーホルダーとなっております。
This is a 3-chain acrylic keyholder featuring three types of outfits: new outfit, default outfit, and Flash Point outfit.
イラストは、「心パズルリズム」の時の、あの後ろにね、可愛いイラスト流れてたんですけれども、でお馴染み、ちぽみるく先生でございます。
The illustrations are by Chipomilku-sensei, famous for the cute illustrations flowing in the background during "Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm."
続いてはこちら。デン！
Next is this. Ta-da!
「新衣装モチーフ ピンバッジセット」
"New Outfit Motif Pin Badge Set"
新衣装をモチーフにしたピンバッジセットですよ。懐中時計、それから今はしてないけどマスク、シルクハット、モノクルの4種類となっております。
This is a pin badge set themed after the new outfit. There are four types: a pocket watch, a mask (which I'm not wearing right now), a top hat, and a monocle.
続いてはこちら。デン！
Next is this. Ta-da!
ボイス！「ライブ前のトラブル！？ボイス」
Voice! "Trouble Before the Live!? Voice"
何が起こるのかは聞いてみてのお楽しみ！
What happens will be a surprise for you to find out!
そしてフルセット購入特典はこちら！デン！
And here is the full set purchase bonus! Ta-da!
はい、儒烏風亭らでん直筆サイン入り、マクラエアン先生描き下ろしポストカード！
Yes! A postcard illustrated by MakuRaen-sensei, hand-signed by Juufuutei Raden!
今回も購入した方全員に直筆でサインを書かせていただきますよ！
I'll be hand-signing them for everyone who purchases again this time!
皆さんに届くように精一杯書かせていただくので、よろしくお願いいたします！
I'll do my absolute best to write them so they reach you all!
さらに特典ボイスもつきます。こちらもらでんが書き下ろしてます！
And a bonus voice is included. I wrote the scenario for this too!
はい！
Yes!
ということで、もう今日ね、もうすごい、すごい盛りだくさんでございましたが、
So, we had so many announcements today,
皆さん追いつけてますか？
are you all keeping up?
結構とんでもない発表たくさんしたんですけれども、
We made some pretty crazy announcements,
らでんが一番結構とんでもないなと思っております。
but I think I'm the one who's most blown away.
ということで、本日の重大発表は、その1：東京国立博物館さんとのコラボ、
So today's major announcements: Number 1, a collab with the Tokyo National Museum;
その2：ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボ、
Number 2, a collab with the London National Gallery;
その3：儒烏風亭らでんがご案内 Pixel Museum ダウンロードコンテンツ発売決定でございます！
and Number 3, the Pixel Museum DLC guided by me has been confirmed!
情報量がね、多すぎたと思うので、ぜひアーカイブでも確認してみて下さい。
There was so much info, so please double-check the archive.
そしてこの後は、メン限でアンコールライブあります！
And after this, we have a member-only encore live show!
その時にまた衣装はゆっくりお見せしようかなと思っております。
I plan to take my time showing you the outfit there.
まだの方はチャンネル登録と、気になるよって方はメンバーでまたアンコールライブでお会いしましょう。
If you haven't, please subscribe, and if you're interested, join the membership and let's meet there!
そしてそして、忘れちゃいけません。このあとすぐ、新曲MV公開でございます！
And of course, we can't forget: right after this, my new song's MV will be released!
頑張って作ったんで、いっぱい見て欲しいです！
I worked really hard on it, so please watch it a lot!
はい！
Yes!
ということでございまして、日頃応援してくださっている皆々様、聴いていただいているリスナーの皆様のおかげで、
Thanks to all of you supporting me daily, and to all of my listeners,
今回ね、このライブを開催することができました。本当に本当にありがとうございます！
we were able to hold this live show today. Thank you so, so much!
とっても嬉しいです！
I'm so incredibly happy!
これからもね、歌もダンスも、自分のやりたいこともいっぱい頑張っていきますので、ぜひ応援のほどよろしくお願いいたします！
I'll keep working hard on singing, dancing, and what I want to do, so please continue supporting me!
それでは、メン限アンコールライブでお会いいたしましょう！
Well then, let's meet at the member-only encore live!
本日の相手は私、儒烏風亭らでんでございました。
Your host for today was me, Juufuutei Raden.
それでは皆さん、良い夜をお過ごしください。さようならでん！
Have a wonderful night, everyone. Sayonara-den!